# Ajay Kumar Dwivedi

A ajaydwivedi.com
Nagpur, Maharashtra, India

♀ github.com/imajaydwivedi 
☐ linkedin.com/in/imajaydwivedi

⟨ (+91) 703-231-2749
 □ ajay.dwivedi2007@gmail.com

# **Professional Summary**

Site Reliability Engineer with 14+ years of experience optimizing SQLServer and PostgreSQL databases, building infrastructure automation using DevOps CI/CD pipelines leveraging scripting tools like PowerShell, Python, Ansible, and GitHub Actions. Leading team in implementing DevOps practices and SRE principles to enhance system reliability and operational efficiency.

#### **Skills**

Databases: SQLServer, PostgreSQL, SQLite, RDS, Managed Instance, Aurora

Programming Languages: 

SQL, 
PowerShell, 
Python, 
JavaScript, 
HTML / CSS, 
Shell Scripting

Tools and Frameworks: Git, Linux, Ansible, Flask, Django, GitHub Actions, VS Code, Grafana, Prometheus, KVM

Virtualization, Container, Podman, Docker, Ubuntu, RHEL, PowerShell DSC, Infrastructure as Code (IaC) **Cloud Platforms:** AWS, Azure

High Availability & Disaster Recovery: Clustering, Availability Groups, Mirroring, Log Shipping, Replication, Disk

Stripping, RAID, Multi Subnet Setup

Languages: English (proficient), Hindi (native)

#### Certifications

Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Querying	Oct 2013
Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Administration	Dec 2013
BrentOzarUnlimited Mastering SQLServer	Nov 2022
SOLSkills Blackbelt Professional	Jun 2023

## **Experience**

## Senior Site Reliability Engineer (DevOps) AngelOne

02 2022 - Present

- Saved 80 hours/week DBA effort with single click Github Action based PostgreSQL Cluster deployment using Ansible Playbook.
- Optimized 10x SQL Server performance with D.E.A.T.H Methodology.
- Saved 1400 hrs/year by automating Transparent Data Encryption (TDE).
- Reduced 80% alerts with query tuning by fixing problems like Ascending Key, Kitchen Sink design, un-even threading, distributed query plans, MSTVFs, etc.
- Reduced 90% incidents by building monitoring and alerting system using PowerShell & Python.
- · Collaborated with Developers and

#### Database Reliability Engineer

05 2020 - 02 2022

- Resolved 100s of incidents by moving 38 TB AG databases with PowerShell.
- Automated/Upgraded 30 Critical SQLClusters/AGs in 12 hours avoiding week long downtime.
- Improved database relibility with automated ScriptOut of entire SOLServer Instances for Disaster Recovery.

**Arcesium** 

## Database Administrator TiV

02 2018 - 05 2020

- Saved 40+ hours by automating SQLServer deployment and configuration using PowerShell.
- Reduced 80% transactional replication issues with latency infra.
- Reduced 80% performance incidents by building Delta Index Defragmentation automation for replicated & HADR databases.

## Senior SQL DBA

## **United Health Group**

10 2016 - 02 2018

- Saved \$1 million/year via DB Space Capacity Automation.
- Improved 50% performance issues with reduced VLDBs maintenance time.

#### **Technical Lead**

# **Ericsson Global**

06 2015 - 10 2016

- 3x Performance Improvement via advanced query optimization like Recursive CTE and Table Partitioning.
- Lead 18+ developers for best practices and guidelines.

#### **SQL DBA Developer**

#### **TATA Consultancy Services**

03 2011 - 06 2015

- Moved 250+ large tables with each having billions of records using SSIS in 45 hours.
- Built data warehouse ETL pipelines using Pentaho & Kettle for high volume Liquor Retail stores.
- Saved 20+ hours/week by Automating core DBA tasks using dynamic SQL.

#### **Education**

# **Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics & Communication Engineering**

RustamJi Institue of Technology

**07 2006 - 06 2010** Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh

#### **Awards and Honors**

**Tech Titan**, AngelOne for 10x Performance Optimization on Prod SQLServer. **Sapphire**, United Health Group for Innovation and automations.

2022

2017

# **Projects**

**SQLMonitor:** Open source Enterprise grade SQLServer monitoring tool

01 2021 - Present

- Built using TSQL, PowerShell, Python, and Grafana.
- Successfully monitoring 500+ SQLServers across environments.
- Observability alerts to Slack, PagerDuty and Email
- Inbuilt auto action to Clear & Resolve

**HadrSync:** PowerShell module that synchronizes all objects across Replicas in Availability Groups

01 2021 - Present

- Ensures zero sync issues during failovers/Drs.
- Detects & synchronizes even delta changes like changes in passwords, definition etc.

# **Availability**

Notice Period: 90 Days

**Relocation:** Open to Relocation **Remote:** Open to remote opportunities

## **FINAL NOTE**

I have problem-solving mindset and love designing efficient database systems and solving complex performance challenges in collaboration with various tech teams. I help organisations build robust, fully automated infrastructure with PowerShell, Python and Ansible.